对称密码学我们快讨论完了
Well, we're almost done with our
discussion of symmetric encryption. There
还有些零零碎碎的东西我这里想讨论一下
are just a couple of odds and ends that
I'd like to discuss before we move on to
然后我们再谈下一话题。首先我想提一下，
如何从一个密钥推出多个密钥
the next topic. So the first thing I'd
like to mention is how we derive many keys
实际上，这点全部来自于实践
from one key. And it, actually, this comes
up all the time in practice, so I'd like
我想确保大家知道，如何正确地操作
to make sure you know how to do this
correctly. So what's the setting that
我们在看什么样的设定？设想我们有一个特定的源密钥
we're looking at? Well, imagine we have a
certain source key that's generated by one
源密钥有很多种方法生成。设想源密钥是由
of a number of methods. Imagine the
source key is generated by a hardware
一个硬件随机数发生器生成的，或者
可能是由密钥交换协议生成的
random number generator or perhaps is
generated by a key exchange protocol
我们稍后讨论密钥交换协议。有很多方法
which we're going to discuss later. But
anyhow, there are a number of ways in
可以生成Alice和Bob之间的源密钥
which a source key might be generated
between Alice and Bob, such that the
这样攻击者不知道源密钥是什么。现在，如我们所说
attacker doesn't know what the source key
is. But now, as we said, in many cases, we
在很多情况下，我们需要很多密钥来保证会话的安全，
不仅仅是单个源密钥
actually need many keys to secure a
session, not just one single source key.
例如，如果大家记得，在TLS里，有一些单向密钥
For example, if you remember, in TLS there
were unidirectional keys and we
我们每个方向都需要不同密钥。事实上在每个方向
needed keys in each direction. And in
fact, in each direction, we needed
我们需要多个密钥。我们需要一个MAC密钥，
我们需要一个加密密钥。我们需要一个IV
multiple keys. We needed a MAC key, we
needed an encryption key. We need an IV,
等等。。类似地还有基于新鲜值的加密，大家记得
and so on. Similarly nonce based
encryption, you remember, there were
使用了多个密钥，等等。那么问题是
multiple keys that were being used, and so
on. And so, the question is, how do we use
我们如何使用一个源密钥，从一个硬件过程
the one source key that we just derived,
either from a hardware process or
或密钥交换，来生成一堆密钥，可以用这些密钥
by key exchange, and generate a bunch of
keys from it that we could then use to
来保证我们的会话安全。这个使用所谓的
secure our session. The way that's done,
is using a mechanism called a key
密钥推导函数(KDF)来实现。我想多讨论一点
derivation function, KDF. And I want to
talk a little bit about how KDF's are
KDF是如何组建的。首先，假设我们有一个安全的PRF
constructed. So first of all, suppose we
have a secure PRF, that happens to have
正好有密钥空间K。现在，假设我们的源密钥SK
key space K. And now, suppose that it so
happens that our source key SK is uniform
在密钥空间K中均匀分布。这时，源密钥实际上是
安全PRF F的一个均匀随机密钥
in the key K. In this case, the source key
is, in fact, a uniform random key for the
我们可以直接使用它来生成多个密钥
secure PRF F. And we can use it directly to
generate keys, all the keys that we need
我们需要这些密钥来保证会话的安全。这种情况下，KDF很简单
to secure the session. So in this case,
the KDF is really simple. The key
这个密钥推导函数如下工作。它取源密钥为输入
derivation function would just work as
follows. It would take as input the
它还取一个参数上下文作为输入
source key. It would take an input, a
parameter context, which I'm gonna
我待会来描述这个参数。取输入的长度作为输入
describe in just a minute. And then it's
gonna take a length input as input as
然后计算PRF在0处的值
well. And then what it will do is it will
basically evaluate the PRF on zero. Then
然后计算PRF在1处的值，然后计算PRF在2处的值，直到L
it will evaluate the PRF on one. Then it
will evaluate the PRF on two, up until L.
我待会讨论这里的上下文
And I will talk about what this context is
in just a second. And then, basically, you
使用输出中你需要的那么多位，来生成
would use as many bits of the output as
you would need to generate all the keys
会话的全部密钥。如果需要生成单向密钥
for the session. So, if you need unidirectional keys you would generate, you
每个方向都有一个密钥，包括加密密钥和一个MAC密钥
know, one key in each direction where each key
might include an encryption key and a MAC
这样，你会生成你需要的那么多位
key. And so, you would basically generate
as many bits as you need and then finally
最后截断输出，当你生成了足够多的密钥来保护会话
cut off the output at the time when you've
generated enough keys to secure your
这是一个很直白的机制
session. Okay so this is a fairly straight
forward mechanism it's basically using the
它使用了安全的PRF作为一个伪随机数发生器。唯一的问题是
secure PRF as a pseudo random generator.
And the only question is what is its
它的上下文字符串。我告诉大家，这个上下文字符串
context string. Well, I'll tell you that
the context string is basically a unique
是一个唯一的字符串，作为应用的身份。所以
实际上你可以在一个系统上有多个应用
string that identifies the application. So
in fact you might have multiple
多个应用试着建立多种安全密钥
applications on the same system that's
trying to establish multiple secure keys.
也许你有一个进程运行SSH，还有另一个进程
运行着网页服务器
Maybe you have SSH running as one process,
you have a web server running as another process,
第三个进程是IPsec，所有这三个进程都有密钥生成
IPsec as a third process and all three need
to have secret keys generated. And this
这个上下文变量试图把他们三个分开。我问大家
context variable basically tries to separate
the three of them. So, let me ask you,
更精确地说，你认为上下文变量的目的是什么？
more precisely, what do you think
the purpose of this context variable is?
我想我已经给出了答案
So I guess I've given
it away and this context variable is
上下文变量用来分离各个进程，比如说
supposed to basically separate
applications, so that even if, for
即使我们刚刚说的这三个服务：SSH，网页服务器和IPsec
example, the three services that we just
talked about, SSH, web server, and IPsec,
如果它们都从硬件的随机数发生器获得了同样的源密钥
if they all happen to obtain the same
source key from the hardware random number
那么由于三个应用的上下文不同
generator then the context since it's
different for the three apps will make
可以确保它们依然获得独立的字符串，可以用来保护会话安全
sure that they still get three independent
strings that they can then use to secure
我就想让大家记住，尽管这个方法很直接
the sessions. I just want you to remember
that, even though this is actually fairly
我们之前也讨论过，上下文字符串是重要的
straightforward, and we discussed this
before, the context string is actually
对应用而言必须是特有的
important, and it does need to be specific
to the application, so that each
使得每个进程有属于自己的会话密钥，
即使多个进程正好有同样的源密钥SK
application gets its own session keys,
even if multiple applications happen to
下个问题是，如果源密钥不是均匀分布的
sample the same SK. The next
question is, what do we do if the source
我们该怎么办？现在我们就有问题了。如果源密钥
key actually isn't uniform? Well, now we
got a problem. If the source key is not a
不是均匀分布的密钥，对于伪随机函数来说，我们不能继续假设
uniform key for the pseudo random function
then we can no longer assume that the
伪随机函数的输出是与随机函数的输出不可区分的了
output of the pseudo random function is
indistinguishable from random. In fact, if
事实上，如果我们只使用我们刚刚描述的KDF，
其输出看起来可能并不随机
we just use the KDF that we just described
then the output might not look random to
这样攻击者可能可以预期某些我们使用的会话密钥
the adversary and then he might be able to
anticipate some of the session keys that
进而破解会话。所以我们有问题了
we'll be using and thereby break the
session. So then we have a problem. Now
为什么这个源密钥会不是随机分布的呢？这有很多原因的
why would this source key not be uniform?
Well there are many reasons why this
比如说，如果你使用一个密钥交换协议
happened. For example if you use a key
exchange protocol, it so happens typically
很可能这个密钥交换协议会生成一个高熵的密钥
that key exchange protocols will generate a
high entropy key. But the
(高熵意味着字符串的分布接近均匀，但不是均匀分布)
高熵的密钥分布于密钥空间的一个子空间
high entropy key is gonna be
distributed in some subspace of the key
那么这个密钥不是均匀分布的字符串
space. So it's not going to be a uniform
string. It will be uniform in some
它会是某个更大集合的子集上的均匀分布。
我们会看些例子，等我们讨论密钥交换协议
subset of a larger set. And we'll see
examples of that as soon as we talk about
所以KDF必须适应密钥交换协议
key exchange protocols. And so KDFs have
to kind of accommodate for the fact that
不能生成均匀分布的字符串这一事实
key exchange protocols actually don't
generate uniform bit strings. The other
另一问题是，事实上，大家使用的硬件随机数发生器
problem is, that, in fact, the hardware
random number generator you're using might
可能也会生成不均匀的输出。我们不想依赖
actually produce biased outputs. We don't
wanna rely on the non bias of the hardware
输出不均匀的硬件随机数发生器。所以我们
只能假设输出结果含有高熵
random number generator. And so all we
want to assume is that it generates a high
但可能是不均匀的。这种情况下
entropy string, but one that might be
biased. In which case, we have to somehow
我们必须从某种意义上清楚这种不均匀。所以
这就引入了这种构建KDF的机制
clean this bias. And so this introduces
this, this paradigm for building KDFs.
叫做先提取再扩展的机制
This is called the extract-then-expand
paradigm, where the first step
KDF的第一步是从实际源密钥中提取一个伪随机密钥
of the KDF is to extract a pseudo random
key from the actual source key. So in a
在这张图里，大家可以想到这点。
某种意义上，源密钥有多种可能的值
picture you can think about it like this.
In some sense these are the different
这条水平线和这条垂直轴
possible values of the source key. This is
the horizontal line and the vertical axis
表示这些值的概率分布，大家可以看到
is basically the probability of each one
of these values, and you can see that this
这是一个分布崎岖的函数，说明源密钥
is a kind of a bumpy function which would
say that the source key is not uniformly
并不是在密钥空间上均匀分布的。这里我们使用
distributed in the key space. What we do
in this case is we use what's called an
所谓的提取器，提取器取这个不均匀的函数为输入
extractor. So an extractor is something
that takes a bumpy distribution and makes
把它变成一个密钥空间上的均匀分布
it into a uniform distribution over the
key space. In our case we're actually just
这里我们使用所谓的计算提取器
gonna be using what are called
computational extractors, namely
这种提取器最后不一定产生均匀分布的输出
extractors that don't necessarily produce
uniform distribution at the end but
但生成的分布与真的均匀分布不可区分
they generated distribution that's
indistinguishable from uniform.
现在提取器取一个盐作为输入
Now extractors typically take as input
something called a salt, and a salt just
就像撒拉里的盐，增加口感
like in a salad, it kind of adds flavor to
things, what it does is basically kind of
这个盐的作用就是捣乱，不管输入分布如何
jumbles things around, so that no matter
what the input distribution is, the output
输出分布依然与随机分布不可区分
distribution is still going to be
indistinguishable from random. So a salt
什么是盐？盐不是秘密的字符串，是公开知道的
basically, what is it? It's a non-secret
string, so it's publicly known. It doesn't
如果攻击者知道盐也无所谓，而且盐是固定的值
matter if the adversary knows what the
salt is, and it's fixed forever. The only
唯一一点是让你选择盐时，你是随机选择的
point is that when you chose it, you chose
one at random. And then the hope is that
试图提取的有趣的分布本质上
the funny distribution that you're trying
to extract from kinda doesn't inherently
并不依赖于你选择的盐，因此使用盐的结果
depends on the salt that you chose and
hence as a result using your salt, you
是得到一个看起来与随机分布不可区分的分布
will actually get a distribution that
looks indistinguishable from random. So
本质上要想获得盐，你可以脸滚键盘几次
essentially the salt, you know, you can
just bang it the keyboard a couple of
只要保证是随机产生的即可
times when you generate it but it just
needs to be something that's random
但是盐永远是固定的。如果攻击者知道盐也无所谓
initially but then it's fixed forever, and
it's fine if the adversary knows what
不过提取器可以提取熵，并输出
it is and nevertheless the extractor is
able to extract the entropy and output a
一个均匀分布的随机字符串K。某种意义上，
盐是用来防御
uniformly random string K. In some sense the
salt is only there to defend against
可能会干扰提取器的恶意的坏分布
adversarially bad distributions that might
mess up our extractor. Okay, so now that
现在我们提取了一个伪随机密钥。我们
可能也会在KDF中使用它
we have extracted a pseudo random key.
Now, we might as well just use it in a KDF
我们刚刚看了使用安全的伪随机函数
that we just saw using a secure
pseudo random function to expand the key
把密钥扩展成我们需要的那么多位，来保证会话安全
into as many bits as we need to actually
secure the session. Okay, so there are
有这两步：首先我们提取一个伪随机密钥
these two steps. The first one is we
extract a pseudo-random key, and then once
然后我们有了一个伪随机密钥，我们已经知道了
然后把它扩展成我们需要的那么多密钥
we have a pseudo-random key we already
know how to extend it into as many keys as
用于伪随机函数。所以标准方法是
we need using a pseudo-random function. So
the standardized way of doing this is
所谓的HKDF，它是一个KDF，是使用HMAC构建的密钥推导函数
called HKDF. This is a KDF, a key derivation function that's built from HMAC.
这里HMAC既用于PRF进行扩展，又用于提取器
And here HMAC is used both as the PRF for
expanding and an extractor for extracting
来提取最初的伪随机密钥。我来解释这是怎么工作的
the initial pseudo-random key. So let me
explain how this works. So in the extract
在提取一步中，我们使用盐，一个公开值
step, we're gonna use our salt which you
remember is a public value just happened to
这个盐是在开始时随机选取的。我们使用这个盐
be generated at random at the beginning of
time. And we use this salt as the HMAC
作为HMAC的密钥。然后我们把源密钥作为HMAC的数据
key. And then the source key we're gonna
use as the HMAC data. So we're kind of
我们使用一个公开值作为一个密钥。不过
using a public value as a key. And
nevertheless, one can argue that HMAC has
可以证实HMAC有提取的性质，使得当我们应用HMAC时
extraction properties, such that, when we
apply HMAC, the resulting key is going to
获得的密钥看起来与随机的不可区分，
假设源密钥有足够的熵
look indistinguishable from random,
assuming that the source key actually has
现在我们有了这个伪随机密码
enough entropy to it. And now that we have
the pseudo random key we're simply going
我们将要使用HMAC作为一个PRF来生成一个会话密钥
to use HMAC as a PRF to generate a
session key of you know as many bits as we
生成我们需要的、用于会话密钥的那么多位。
我们对HKDF的讨论差不多就这些
need for the session keys. Okay. So that
basically concludes our discussion of
我只想让大家记住，一旦有了源密钥
HKDF. And I just want you to remember
that, once you obtain a source key, either
从硬件或密钥交换协议得来的，你把它转换成会话密钥
from hardware or from a key exchange
protocol, the way you convert it into
不是通过使用直接的取样。永远不要直接使用源密钥
session keys is not by using that sample
directly. You would never use a source key
作为协议里的会话密钥
directly as a session key in a protocol.
What you would do is you will run the
将源密钥交给一个KDF，KDF会给你所有的密钥
source key through a KDF. And the KDF
would give you all the keys and output
和你需要的输出，比如随机性、协议要用到的随机密钥
that you need, for, the randomness, for
the random keys to be used in your
一个典型的KDF是HKDF，这里讨论了很多
protocol. And a typical KDF to use is
HKDF, which is actually getting quite a
本节我想讨论的最后一个话题是
bit of traction out there. Okay. The last
topic I wanna talk about in this segment
如何从密码中提取密钥。这些通常叫做
is, how do you extract keys from
passwords. These are called password based
基于密码的KDF，或PBKDF。这里的问题是
密码通常含有较低的熵
KDFs or PBKDFs. The problem here is
that passwords have relatively low
事实上，我们将在本课程稍后讨论密码
entropy. In fact, we're gonna talk about
passwords later on in the course when we
等我们讨论用户认证时。所以我这里不打算讲太多
talk about user authentication. And so,
I'm not gonna say too much here. I'll just
我只说密码通常含有很小的熵，约为20位左右的熵
say passwords generally have very little
entropy estimated on the order of twenty
因此，这点熵对于根据密码生成会话密钥来说是不够的
bits of entropy, say. And as a result,
there is simply not enough entropy to
我们还经常需要做这件事
generate session keys out of a password.
And yet we still need to do it very
我们需要根据密码推导加密密钥和MAC密钥
frequently. We still need to derive
encryption keys and MACs and so on out of
那么问题是怎么做？首先
passwords, so the question is how to do
it. The first thing is, you know, for this
出于这种目的的话，不要使用HKDF，其设计与我们的目标不符
kind of purpose, don't use HKDF. That's
not what it's designed for. What will
若使用HKDF，推导出的密钥对所谓的字典攻击是脆弱的
happen is that the derived keys will
actually be vulnerable to something called
我们将在本课程稍后讨论字典攻击
a dictionary attack, which we're gonna
talk about much later in the course when
等我们讨论用户认证时。那么PBKDF防御
we talk about user authentication. So, the
way PBKDFs defend against this low entropy
造成字典攻击的低熵问题，通过两种手段
problem that results in a dictionary
attack is by two means. First of all, as
首先，在使用盐前，盐是一个公开的固定值
before they use a salt, a public,
random value that's fixed forever. But in
PBKDF还使用一个所谓的慢哈希函数
addition, they also use what's called a
slow hash function. And let me describe
我来描述一种从密码推导密钥的标准方法，叫做PKCS #5
kind of the standard approach to deriving
keys from passwords. This is called PKCS #5,
特别地，我要讨论的版本是PBKDF1
and in particular, the version I'll describe
is what's called PBKDF1. And I
(现已有更新的版本PBKDF2)
我应该说下，这个机制在大多数密码学库中都已实现
should say that this mechanism is
implemented in most crypto libraries so
你不应该自己去实现
you shouldn't have to implement this
yourself. All you would do, you know, you
你只要调用一个函数，由密码推导密钥
would call a function, you know, derived
key from password. You would give the
给密码作为输入，你会得到一个密钥作为输出
password in as input, and you would get a
key as output. But you should be aware of
不过大家应该意识到，这个密钥当然没有高熵
course that this key is not going to have
high entropy so in fact it will be
所以事实上是可以猜出的。这些PBKDF试图让这个猜测问题
guessable. What these PBKDFs try to do is
make the guessing problem as hard as
尽可能的困难。它们是这样工作的，首先，如我们所说
possible. Okay. So the way they work,
first of all, is, as we said, they
它们计算密码联结上盐后，所得字符串的哈希值
basically hash, the concatenation of the
password and the salt. And then the hash
然后这个哈希函数被设计成一个非常慢的哈希函数
itself is designed to be a very slow hash
function. And the way we build a slow hash
构造一个慢哈希函数的方法是取一个特定的哈希函数
比如说，SHA-256
function is by taking one particular hash
function, say, SHA-256, and we
我们迭代它很多次，记为C次。那么你可以想象有1000次
iterate it many, many times, C times. So
you can imagine 1000 times, perhaps even a
也可能有一百万次。我说的迭代是什么意思？
million times. And what do I mean by
iterating it? So, well, we take the
我们取密码和盐。我们把它们放在这个哈希函数的输入里
password and the salt. And we put them
inside of one input to the hash function.
然后我们应用哈希函数，我像这样写
And then we apply the hash function, oops,
let me write it like this. And then we
然后我们应用哈希函数，获得一个输出，
然后我们再应用哈希函数
apply the hash function and we get an
output, and then we apply the hash
获得另一个输出。我们一次又一次地这样做
function again and we get another output.
And we do this again and again and again
也许一千次或一百万次，取决于你的处理器有多快
maybe a thousand times or a million times
depending on how fast your processors are
最终我们获得了最后的输出
and then finally we get the final output
that we actually output as, as the key
作为这个密钥推导函数的密钥输出。要点是什么？
output of this key derivation function.
Now what is the point here? Iterating a
迭代函数一万次或甚至一百万次，在现代处理器上
function 10,000 times or even a million
times is going to take very little time on
只需要很短的时间，因此它不怎么影响用户体验
a modern CPU, and as a result, it doesn't
really affect the user's experience. The
用户输入他的密码，它会哈希一百万次，获得输出
user types in his password, it gets hashed
a million times and then it gets output.
也许那需要十分之一秒，用户不会注意到
And maybe that could even take, you know a
tenth of a second and the user wouldn't
但攻击者可以尝试字典里的所有密码
even notice it. However the attacker, all
he can do is he can try all the passwords
因为我们知道人们更愿意选择字典里的密码
in the dictionary, because we know people
tend to pick passwords in dictionaries,
所以攻击者可以一个一个地尝试，记得盐是公开的
and so he could just try them one by one,
remember the SALT is public, so he knows
所以攻击者知道盐，那么他可以一个一个地尝试这个哈希
what the SALT is. And so he can just try this
hash one by one. However because the hash
但是因为这个哈希函数很慢，每一次尝试都要
花掉他十分之一秒的时间
function is slow, each attempt is gonna
take him a tenth of second. So if he needs
所以如果他需要跑完一个字典，字典里有2千亿个密码
to run through a dictionary, you know, with,
with a 200 billion passwords in it,
因为哈希函数速度慢，这要花掉攻击者很长的时间
because the hash function is slow, this is
gonna take quite awhile. And by doing
通过这样做，我们减缓了字典攻击，使得攻击者
that, we slow down the dictionary attack,
and we make it harder for the attacker to
更难猜中我们的会话密钥。虽不是不可能，但更困难
这就是PBKDF1所做的一切
get our session keys. Not impossible, just
harder. That's all this is trying to do.
这就是关于基于密码的KDF我想说的
Okay, so this is basically what I wanted
to say about password based KDFs. As I
如我所说，这不是大家自己去构建的
said, this is not something you would
build yourself. All crypto libraries have
所有的密码学库都有PKCS #5机制的实现
an implementation of a PKCS #5
mechanism. And you would just call the
你只需要合理地调用函数，就能把一个密码
转换成一个密钥，然后就能使用获得的密钥了
appropriate function to convert a password
into a key, and then use the resulting
下节我们将看如何使用对称加密
key. Okay, in the next segment, we're
gonna see how to use symmetric encryption
来在密文上进行搜索
in a way that allows us to search on the
cipher texts.